<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!--DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd' []-->

<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space
    (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="std"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    docName="draft-ietf-brissette-evpn-address-resolution-00"
    consensus="true"
    submissionType="IETF"
    ipr="trust200902"
    tocInclude="true"
    tocDepth="4"
    symRefs="true"
    sortRefs="true">

 <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

 <front>
   <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the
        full title is longer than 39 characters -->
   <title abbrev="EVPN IP Address Resolution">EVPN IP Address Resolution Extension</title>

   <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

   <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->
  <author fullname="Patrice Brissette" initials="P." surname="Brissette" role="editor">
     <organization>Cisco</organization>
     <address>
       <email>pbrisset@cisco.com</email>
     </address>
   </author>

   <author fullname="Jiri Chaloupka" initials="J." surname="Chaloupka">
     <organization>Cisco</organization>
     <address>
       <email>jichalou@cisco.com</email>
     </address>
   </author>

   <author fullname="Jorge Rabadan" initials="J." surname="Rabadan">
     <organization>Nokia</organization>
     <address>
       <email>jorge.rabadan@nokia.com</email>
     </address>
   </author>

   <author fullname="David Ward" initials="D." surname="Ward">
     <organization>PacketFabric</organization>
     <address>
       <email>dward@packetfabric.com</email>
     </address>
   </author>

   <author fullname="Satoru Matsushima" initials="S." surname="Matsushima">
     <organization>Softbank</organization>
     <address>
       <email>satoru.matsushima@g.softbank.co.jp</email>
     </address>
   </author>

   <author fullname="Daniel Bernier" initials="D." surname="Bernier">
     <organization>Bell Canada</organization>
     <address>
       <email>daniel.bernier@bell.ca</email>
     </address>
   </author>

<!--
   <author fullname="Andy Karch" initials="A.K." surname="Karch">
     <organization>Cisco</organization>
     <address>
       <email>akarch@cisco.com</email>
     </address>
   </author>
   -->

   <date year="2023" />

   <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->
   <area>General</area>
   <workgroup>BESS Working Group</workgroup>

   <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
        IETF is fine for individual submissions.
        If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
        which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

   <keyword>EVPN</keyword>
   <keyword>IP address resolution</keyword>

   <abstract>
     <t>This document presents an enhanced control plane for Ethernet VPN (EVPN)
     that eliminates the need for data plane flooding of ARP/ND messages.
     EVPN enables hosts to communicate within the same subnet, and the current
     EVPN E-LAN solution relies on data plane flooding for IP address resolution.
     This proposed solution aims to reduce flooding and optimize communication
     in large-scale networks.
    </t>
   </abstract>

   <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t> The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>
      and <xref target="RFC8174">RFC 8174</xref>.
      </t>
    </note>
 </front>

 <middle>
   <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
    <t>
    Ethernet VPN (EVPN) solutions, as defined in <xref target="RFC7432"/>,
    facilitate communication between connected endpoints (CE) or hosts that
    share the same subnet. This communication utilizes broadcast and multicast
    forwarding, also known as flooding, which is a common behavior in Layer-2
    networks. However, this flooding behavior can pose challenges for some
    providers, leading to unpredictable patterns and increased bandwidth
    consumption in their networks. Moreover, it may expose security risks,
    potentially enabling malicious users to launch DDoS attacks.
	  </t>

    <t>
    While <xref target="RFC9161"/> has made significant progress in reducing
    flooding over EVPN networks through ARP/ND proxy behavior, certain aspects
    remain unresolved. The initial sign of life messaging when a CE/host
    connects to the network is not addressed. Intra-subnet communication relies
    on neighbor discovery protocols (ARP/ND), where ARP requests and Neighbor
    Solicitation (NS) messages are flooded across the Layer-2 core network to
    all remote devices connected to that subnet.
    </t>

    <t>
    Unfortunately, in a large-scale network, this flood of three or more
    broadcast/multicast messages from CE/hosts to discover remote CE/hosts can
    lead to unpredictable flooding storms. Some deployments resort to
    provisioning static ARP/ND entries to mitigate this behavior. However,
    maintaining such a list of static entries proves to be costly and cumbersome,
    especially when adding or removing new CE/hosts.
    </t>

     <section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">
        <t>
         <dl>
		 	<dt>CE:</dt><dd>Customer Edge Router</dd>
		 	<dt>DAD:</dt><dd>IPv6 Duplicate Address Detection message</dd>
		 	<dt>GARP:</dt><dd>Gratuitous ARP message</dd>
			<dt>NA:</dt><dd>IPv6 Neighbor Advertisement message</dd>
			<dt>ND:</dt><dd>IPv6 Neighbor Discovery</dd>
		 	<dt>NS:</dt><dd>IPv6 Neighbor Solicitation message</dd>
      <dt>PE:</dt><dd>Provider Edge Router</dd>
			<dt>Request / Solicitation:</dt><dd>The term request is widely used in this
		    document. It refers to ARP request for IPv4 or ND solicitation for IPv6.</dd>
			<dt>RPL:</dt><dd>Route Policy Language</dd>
			<dt>RT-2:</dt><dd>Referring to EVPN route type-2 (MAC/IP)</dd>
        </dl>
	    </t>
     </section>
   </section>

   <section anchor="CP-solution" title="Address Resolution Solution">

	<t>
  This document proposes a new solution extending the EVPN control-plane where
  the IP address resolution is performed from control-plane rather than
  data-plane. The procedure leverages ARP/ND proxy capabilities as described
  in <xref target="RFC9161"/>. The following section describes the behaviour to
  perform ARP resolution. Neighbor Discovery Protocol works in a similar manner.
	</t>

        <figure><preamble/><artwork><![CDATA[

	+-----+     +-----+   +---------+   +-----+     +-----+
	| CE1 |-----| PE1 |---|   CORE  |---| PE2 |-----| CE2 |
	+-----+     +-----+   |    L2   |   +-----+     +-----+
	MAC: M1               +---------+               MAC: M2
	IP: IP1                                         IP: IP2
            ]]>
        </artwork><postamble>Layer-2 Network</postamble></figure>

  <t>
  This picture shows a simple layer-2 network where a common subnet is shared across CE1
  and CE2. PE1 and PE2 support the new IP address resolution procedure.
  </t>

	<t>
  In this example, CE1 initiates the communication with CE2 using ARP
  protocol. The new procedure is as follow:

	<list style="numbers">
		<t>CE1 sends ARP requests to PE1 with destination IP=IP2 and broadcast MAC
    address as destination address.
    </t>

		<t>PE1 punts incoming ARP requests to control-plane. Data-plane floods
    these requests to all locally connected ACs (in the same broadcast domain)
    only and avoids the replication / flooding to any remote PEs over the L2 core.
    </t>

		<t>PE1 learns the CE1 ARP request entry in control-plane to keep track of
    this request.  PE1 creates a single new BGP-EVPN IP address resolution
    route, which is advertised to remote PEs (PE2). Basically, it requests all
    remote PEs to look for a specific IP address which may be connected for
    probing purpose.
    </t>

		<t>PE2 receives a single IP address resolution route and triggers local
    CE2 ARP request to all locally connected ACs in the same broadcast domain.
    PE2 uses CE1 source MAC/IP per ARP request towards connected CEs for
    transparency. PE2 performs local probing for specific destination IP2
    address. This becomes a local behaviour from PE2 point-of-view.
		</t>

		<t>CE2 receives the ARP request and sends an ARP reply with its own information.</t>

		<t>The reply may be punted to control-plane on PE2 where the new MAC_CE2 and
    IP_CE2 binding is created. The PE2 advertises to PE1 via existing EVPN RT2
    (MAC+IP) the CE2 host information. CE2s ARP Reply may also be forwarded
    based on a lookup on the destination MAC address via the layer-2 data-plane.
		</t>

		<t> PE1 may create local MAC/IP binding entry in control-plane based on
    received BGP EVPN RT-2.  Based on the ARP request entry learned initially,
    PE1 creates an ARP reply message and send it to CE1.  PE1 uses CE2_MAC +
    CE2_IP for this ARP reply. Optionally, a GARP may be transmitted in
    replacement of the ARP reply as recommended per <xref target="RFC9161"/> when ARP proxy
    is in use.
		</t>

		<t>PE1 marks the initial CE2 request as resolved in control-plane.
    The associated IP address resolution route advertised in BGP is withdrawn.</t>
	</list>
	</t>

	</section>

	<section anchor="IP-res-nlri" title="BGP EVPN Address Resolution Route">

            <t>The IP address resolution procedure requires a new BGP route in EVPN.
            The BGP EVPN NLRI as defined in <xref target="RFC7432"/> is shown below:

            <figure><preamble/><artwork><![CDATA[
            +-----------------------------------+
            |    Route Type (1 octet)           |
            +-----------------------------------+
            |     Length (1 octet)              |
            +-----------------------------------+
            | Route Type specific (variable)    |
            +-----------------------------------+
                        ]]>
                </artwork><postamble>BGP EVPN NLRI</postamble></figure>
            </t>
            <t>This document defines an additional route type (TBD) in the IANA
            "EVPN Route Types" registry [EVPNRouteTypes] to be used for the
            advertisement of EVPN probing route:
            <ul>
                <li>Value:  TBD</li>
                <li>Description: IP Address Resolution</li>
            </ul>
            </t>

            <t>For backward interoperability, a node that does not recognize
            the route type TBD (RT-TBD) will ignore it.</t>

            <t>The detailed encoding of this route and associated procedures are
            described in the following sections.</t>

    	<section anchor="IP Address Resolution Probing Encoding" title="Address Resolution Encoding">

            <t>An EVPN IP Address Resolution route type for IPv4 or IPv6 consists of
			 the following fields:
            <figure anchor="NLRI"><preamble/><artwork><![CDATA[
            +----------------------------------------+
            |      RD (8 octets)                     |
            +----------------------------------------+
            | Ethernet Segment Identifier (10 octets)|
            +----------------------------------------+
            | Ethernet Tag ID (4 octets)             |
            +----------------------------------------+
            | Source MAC address (6 octets)          |
            +----------------------------------------+
            | Destination MAC address (6 octets)     |
            +----------------------------------------+
            | Source IP Prefix Len                   |
            |    (1 octet, 0 to 32 or 128)           |
            +----------------------------------------+
            | Source IP Prefix (4 or 16 octets)      |
            +----------------------------------------+
            | Destination IP Prefix Len              |
            |    (1 octet, 0 to 32 or 128)           |
            +----------------------------------------+
            | Destination IP Prefix (4 or 16 octets) |
            +----------------------------------------+
                    ]]>
                    </artwork><postamble>EVPN Address Resolution Route NLRI for
					IPv4 and IPv6</postamble></figure>
                </t>

            <t>Where:
            <list style="symbols">
            <t>The Length field of the BGP EVPN NLRI for an EVPN IP Address
			      Resolution route
            MUST be either 44 (if IPv4 addresses are carried) or 68 (if IPv6
            addresses are carried). The source and destination IP prefixes MUST
            be from the same IP address family.</t>

            <t>The Route Distinguisher (RD) and Ethernet Tag ID MUST be used as
            defined in <xref target="RFC7432"/>. In particular, the RD is unique
            per MAC-VRF.</t>

            <t>The Ethernet Segment Identifier may be a non-zero 10-octet
            identifier. It identifies the first-hop interface when an ESI is configured.
            The ESI format is described in <xref target="RFC7432"/>. </t>

            <t>The source MAC address is the one from the CE originating the
            IP address resolution request.</t>

            <t>The destination MAC address is the one received from the request on
            the first-hop PE. It can either be set to broadcast MAC address or be set
            to a specific value when the PE is dealing with a unicast request.</t>

            <t>The source IP prefix length can be set to a value between 0 and 32 (bits)
            for IPv4 and between 0 and 128 for IPv6, and it specifies the
            number of bits in the prefix. The value MUST NOT be greater than
            128.</t>

            <t>The source IP prefix is a 4- or 16-octet field (IPv4 or IPv6). The value is
            set to the source IP address of the originator of the request.</t>

            <t>The destination IP prefix length can be set to a value between 0 and 32 (bits)
            for IPv4 and between 0 and 128 for IPv6, and it specifies the
            number of bits in the prefix. The value MUST NOT be greater than
            128.</t>

            <t>The destination IP prefix is a 4- or 16-octet field (IPv4 or IPv6). The value is
            set to the targeted IP address of the incoming request. </t>
			</list>
			</t>

            <t>The RD, Ethernet Tag ID, source and destination MAC, source and destination
			      IP prefix length and IP prefix are part of
            the route key used by BGP to compare routes. The rest of the fields
            are not part of the route key.</t>
        </section>
    </section>

	<section anchor="Considerations" title="Considerations">

  	<t> There are clear reasons for the usage of a new EVPN BGP route type to
    perform IP address resolution:

		<list style="symbols">
		<t>Possible prioritization of routes exchange between PE (importance of ARP/ND
      request/solicitation compare to other routes).</t>

		<t>Specific manipulation over each IP address resolution request and response (security
      feature, RPL, etc.).</t>

		<t>Usage of dedicate route reflector for scalability and performance to handle specifically
		any address resolution routes.</t>

		<t>Backward interoperability with current machinery. For instance, the
    extension of RT-2 to achieve similar behaviour is inappropriate. Existing
    deployed routers may explicit use RT-2 routes for forwarding purpose only.
    </t>

		<t>Provides behavioural transparency by carrying source host MAC and IP address to remote PEs.</t>
		</list>
		</t>
        <section anchor="ESI usage" title="Usage of ESI field">
            <t>The ESI field is meaningful when CE/host is connected to
            multi-homed PE running all-active load-balancing mode. Its purpose
            is to avoid unnecessary probing towards the originating CE/host
            from where the initial request was sourced.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="Originator address" title="Originating Address">
        <t>MAC address and IP address of the originating CE are transmitted
		as part of the new NLRI. They serve multiple purposes:</t>
		<list style="symbols">
		<t>Allow remote PE to reconstruct the ARP/ND request packet as if
		it was received from the data-plane. The targeted CE won't notice the difference
		between control-plane based and data-plane based solutions.</t>

		<t>Allow multiple CE/host to send ARP/ND request towards the same destination.
		Having the source MAC and IP has part of the NLRI key keep all routes unique.</t>

		<t>Allow PE to provide security check over the source.</t>
		</list>
        </section>

		<section anchor="ns-on-egress-PE" title="Rebuilding NS message on Egress PE">
			<t>In the case of IPv6, the neighbor solicitation (NS) message
            MUST be built as specified in <xref target="RFC4861"/> sections 4.3
            and 7.2.2 for the address lookup NS message.
           </t><t>
            The Source IP address and the Link Layer Address in the SLLOA option
            MUST be set to the  Source IP Prefix and the Source MAC address
            in the EVPN Address Resolution Route NLRI <xref target="NLRI"/>,
            respectively.
           </t><t>
            The target address MUST be set to the Destination IP Prefix field of
            the NLRI, and the IP destination address is solicited-node multicast
            address (SNMA) corresponding to the target address a mandated by
            <xref target="RFC4861"/>.
            </t><t>
            The receiver is expected to use the SLLAO and not the source MAC to
            reply.
            At Layer-2, the source MAC MUST be that of the sender (this node).
            The receiver is expected to use the SLLAO and not the source MAC to
            build its neighbor cache entry (NCE). If the receiver is not
            compliant and uses the source MAC instead, this router will
            receive and route the packets from the receiver to the source IP.
            </t><t>
            The destination SHOULD be set to the multicast MAC address
            associated to the SNMA (see section 7 of <xref target="RFC2464"/>
            for Ethernet, unless the source already knows a possible MAC address
            for the destination in which case, the unicast MAC MUST be tried
            first.
            </t>
		</section>

	</section>
<!--
  <section anchor="Flags" title="Notes on some ARP/ND scenarios">
			<t>
      The procedure described in this document solves problems regarding CE/Host
      address resolution. This section explains some ARP/ND corner cases and their
      expected outcomes.</t>

			<t><list style="symbols">
				<t>Gratuitous ARP (GARP):
        <t>GARP messages from CE/host are usually sent when its MAC/IP association
        has changed. EVPN route type-2 with the new binding is generated
        and advertised to remote PEs where their respective forwarding
        tables are updated. EVPN mobility procedure is then performed where GARP
        is transmitted towards remote CE as per <xref target="RFC9161"/> section 3.2.
        </t>
        </t>
				<t>IPv4 probes (ARP request with sender's IP address = 0.0.0.0):
        <t>ARP probing remains only active between router and connected CE/host.
        ARP proxy behaviour is not affected. The source IP address should be taken from
        the gateway interface.
        </t>
        </t>
				<t>IPv6 DAD messages:
        <t>
        The assumption with EVPN is to have a full entry table from BGP as per
        <xref target="RFC9161"/>. DAD messages do not need to be sent over WAN network.
        </t>
        </t>
				<t>IPv6 NS messages:
        <t>
        Neighbor solicitation messages from CE/hosts are not broadcasted over WAN
        network. They trigger the address resolution procedure described in this
        document.
        </t>
        </t>
        <t>IPv6 NUD messages:
        <t>
        These messages are unicast data packets. They goes directly to remote PE
        via the L2 unicast forwarding data-plane.
        </t>
        </t>
        <t>IPv6 RS and RA messages:
        <t>
        Router solicitation and advertisements is completely out-of-scope. There
        is no intent for this draft to provide a solution. The present document
        is geared towards CE/host address resolution.
        </t>
        </t>
        <t> ARP/ND flags:
        <t>
        The propagation of ARP/ND flags as described in <xref target="RFC9047"/>
			  appended to the EVPN address resolution route has been left for further study.
        </t>
        </t>
			</list>

			</t>

	  again if we need to translate NA messages we do need them. It depends on
		the other discussion.. if we want to get rid of GARPs and unsolicited NA messages,
        we will also need to add the ARP/ND extended community to the route.
		- If we want to supress all ARP/ND flooding, it is not only normal ARP Requests and NS
		messages, but also:
		+ GARPs (broadcast reply messages)
		+ unsolicited NA messages
		+ IPv4 probes (ARP requests with sender's ip = 0.0.0.0)
		+ IPv6 DAD messages
	</section>
-->
      <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
        <t>The mechanisms in this document use EVPN control-plane as defined in
        <xref target="RFC7432"/>. Security considerations described in
        <xref target="RFC7432"/> are equally applicable. This document uses MPLS
        and IP-based tunnel technologies to support data-plane transport.
        Security considerations described in <xref target="RFC7432"/> and in
        <xref target="RFC8365"/> are equally applicable.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">

        <t>This document requests the allocation of value TBD in the "EVPN Route
        Types" registry defined by <xref target="RFC7432"/> and modification of the registry
        as follows:
    <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
    Value     Description                Reference
    xxx       Address Resolution route   [this document]
        ]]></artwork></figure>
        </t>
      </section>
    </middle>

 <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

<back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2464.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4861.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7432.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8365.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.9161.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.9047.xml"?>
    </references>
<!--
    <references title="Informative References">
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5905.xml"?>
    </references>

    <section anchor="contributors" title="Contributors">
    <t>In addition to the authors listed on the front page, the following co-authors
    have also contributed substantially to this document:</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
        <t>Authors would like to acknowledge helpful comments
        and contributions of xxx and yyyy.</t>
    </section>
-->

</back>
</rfc>

